
Rules of thumb.

Show as much data as possible: maximize the data density.
 
Make the data stand out: maximize the data-ink ratio. 

If it has been done well in the past, use it. 

Iterate and experiment with graphical display

do not hesiate to make two or more plots of hte same data to make a point

=========================================================================
	
Avoid using unnecessary backgound images, three-dimensional blocks instead of bars, 
fancy borders, and other chart junk.

Use visually prominent graphical elements to show data. 

Data points
	Use large plotting symbols

	When points overlap use plotting symbols to distinguish the overlap, or use
	separate plotting symbols to denote the number of points overlapping, or 
	jitter the points so that they do not overlap 

	Do not let lines obscure data points.

	Keep points off the scale lines.


Tick Marks 
	Graph data in context, eg. supply tick mark labels.

	Keep tick marks outside of data region.

	Use 3-10 tick marks on a scale line.

	Choose range of tick marks to include all or nearly all of the data

  
Scale
	Choose a scale such that the data occupy a large part of the data region.

	Surround graph on all sides with scale lines.

	Do not change scales in mid-axis. Instead use separate panels, and if 
	possible keep the units per centimeter constant accross panels. 

	With mulitple panels in a graph, keep scales the same across panels unless
	there is a problem with resolution

	Consider showing two scales, on oppostie sides of the data region, eg. age in
	years and date of birth, log-scale and orginal scale, or units and percent
	change from base.

	Do not insist that 0 be included on the scale.

   
Additional information
	Put notes in legend

	Keep data region clear of keys and reference markers if they obscure the data 

	Label legibly, completely, correctly, and unambiguously.

	Use a reference marker rather than a reference line if the precision
	is not needed

	Make reference lines less prominent than data lines.

	Make graphs and legends stand alone, i.e. not dependent on the information
	provided in the text of the document.

Honor the visual metaphor altogether. For example, do not use three dimensional
plots to portray one-dimensional data.
    
Do not present information in two or three dimensions when it is one-dimensional.  

Plot time-series data on a time scale.
In a time series, time typically goes on the horizontal scale
       
Layout
	Emphasize the important comparison. For example, with two categorical 
	variables, make it easy to compare groups of the important category. 
	
	Do not jiggle the baseline, that is,
	 
	When the data points have labels, do not order the data alphabetically
	by label, but according to the size of the variable being graphed. 
 
More is murkier, more decimal places, more dimensions, more colors, etc.
  
Scale

   scale of observations versus scale of variable.
       observed range verus range meta information

Resolution

Maintain the shape data 
	put tick marks outside data region

Iterating based on the contents/views of one plot
to get another.  Think of changing scale, examining
the residuals to understand the residual structure
to plot an auxillary.

   standardizing/scaling, baselines, 
   Log transformation
   Residuals
