All univariate plots suck in some ways.
But they are all useful, especially when
  customized with color, glyph. 
  used with multiple variables  on the same plot
  or added to multi-dimensional plots, e.g. margins on a scatterplot, rugs
                                            on a dendogram

  examples
   illustrate the different ways to combine and what one can see.

Go from univariate to specific multivariate/composite.

   Start with a set of numbers (sample)
      rug
      histogram
       compare plot views
      second set of numbers (i.e. new sample)
        compare the distributions using what plot
          categorically located rugs (stripchart(x,y)
          superimposed/juxtaposed histograms
      suppose before and after measurements => relationship across observational units
         parallel coords
         scatterplot
         difference => univariate -> histogram


<lookup>Synthetic or real data? 
Do we have to use concrete examples from real data
and risk switching between datasets to illustrate
points. Probably a mixture of both.
Synthetic is okay here because we are using the computer to
generate it. So it is simulation!  Additionally, we will
use GUIs to control properties of the plots.
</lookup>

Summary:
   Rapid tour of the plot types weaving between univariate and multi and composite
   Then introduce other plot types and what they are good for in the same manner.
   Connect the plot types.
      stacked bar chart -> side by side (bars within a plot and multiple plots)
       -> boxplots or time series example in Bill's Book on doctorates awarded
       by year and program/faculty.


Introduce a scatterplot 
    visualize display using GGobi and R.
       identify mode
       identify across plots - linked plots.

       identify in R from GGobi - i.e. an event in GGobi
         handled in R that then prints to the console the
         entire record.

       spreadsheet - Gnumeric plugin for GGobi.


Exhaust the standard plot types







Quantitative - continuous
	Rug, point graph/strip chart 
	 	Uses: Used at the bottom of a scatterplot to see one-dimensional 
		distribution of the two variables.
		Also used for comparing groups of data (multiple point graphs 
		juxtaposed side-by-side on the same graph).
		When there are few data, the rug can show their positions.  

		Construction aspects: The data points are plotted along a line 
		(invisible for a point graph). For a run, the scale line is used.
		If there is overlap in a point graph, then the plotting symbols are
		moved slightly off the line to distinguish them. 
		 
		How to read: look for range, clumping, gaps, outliers. 

		Dangers: difficult to see anything with significant overlap of 
		data points 

		R-command: hist(), breaks, freq, probability, axes,


	Histogram
	 	Uses: Shows the general shape of the distribution of values.

		Construction aspects: area = percent or count, end point convention,
		discrete values (e.g. soda consumption). Unequal bin widths can
		better portray the shape of the distriubtion, eg. narrow bins in
		the peak areas and wide bins in the tail areas.
		 
		How to read: The histogram portrays data density. Look for peaks, 
		modality, tails, and symmetry. Approximate quantiles can be read
		from a histogram.

		Dangers: Do not mistake for a bar graph. The bin-width can 
		significantly change the view of the distribution, and the 
		precision. 

		R-command: hist(), breaks, freq, probability, axes,


	Box graph
	 	Uses: A visual presentation of five percentiles (10, 25, 50, 75, 
		and 90) and possible outliers. 

<question>
Does the box help comparisons across boxplots
by giving an individual object to compare ``on top'' of the
dashed lines</question>

		Construction aspects: Box denotes the upper and lower quantiles with
		the median marked in the box. the whiskers extend from either end of 
		the box to the 10/90th percentile. Observations beyond the whiskers
		are denoted with separate plotting symbols.
		 
		How to read: tails, symmetry, outliers, specific quantiles.
		Most useful in comparisons across groups.

		Dangers: the width of the box does not have any meaning, symmetry and
		modality may be hidden. there are many variations on the boxplot,
		be sure you know what the box and whiskers denote.

		R-command: hist(), breaks, freq, probability, axes,


	Percentile plot - Empirical CDF
	 	Uses: 

		Construction aspects: 
		 
		How to read: 

		Dangers: 

		R-command: 


	Normal quantile plot
	 	Uses: 

		Construction aspects: 
		 
		How to read: 

		Dangers: 

		R-command: 


	Parallel Coordinates


Category
	Bar chart
	 	Uses: 

		Construction aspects: 
		 
		How to read: 

		Dangers: 

		R-command: 

	Dot chart
	 	Uses: 

		Construction aspects: 
		 
		How to read: 

		Dangers: 

		R-command: 

 	Pie chart
	 	Uses: 

		Construction aspects: 
		 
		How to read: 

		Dangers: 

		R-command: 

	Table
	 	Uses: 

		Construction aspects: 
		 
		How to read: 

		Dangers: 

		R-command: 

        Mosaic plots


Quantitative - discrete

  ordered factors
