<?xml version="1.0"?>

<section>
<title>Documentation for R</title>

There are a numerous books written about different aspects of S for
different audiences.  The books are primarily written for S-Plus, the
commercial version of the S language.  Only recently have ones emerged
for R.  However, most of the material applies to both so reading a
book based on S-Plus will be valuable when applied to R.  In addition
to books that you can get from the library or buy, there are on-line
manuals for R covering different topics from a introduction, to a
reference manual, to importing and exporting data, to extending the
system with packages, etc.  See <ulink
href="http://cran.r-project.org">R Web site</ulink>.  And there are
contributed documents that provide different introductions to R with
different perspectives (and even different languages).  See <ulink
href="http://cran.r-project.org">contributed introductions</ulink>.

The books are 
<>

There are mailing lists to which people post questions about aspects
of R. The R-help list is the most likely one to be of value to people
using R for general purpose statistical and programming tasks.  The
list is archived so that people can look for previous questions and
related answers and hopefully find the answer to their question.
While the lists are helpful, they rely on voluntary contributions by
the R developers and users. They are not for answering homework
questions and are not a substitute for trying to find the answer in
the documentation. They are meant as a resource for finding answers to
unusual questions that are not covered in the documentation.  So do
your homework before asking the list.  But don't be put off in
general.  For the purpose of the class, it is useful to send mail to
the class mailing list. You are likely to get input from me, the TA,
or your classmates who might already know the answer or who can help
to discover the answer.


</section>



Frank Harrell

Mike Friendly

R manuals on CRAN

R tutorials


www.MySQL.org

Perl
<link url="www.Perl.com">Perl</link>

<link url="http://en.wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</link>


