<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<article>

<title>Email and Statistics</title> Email is being used increasingly
by a large number of people, at least in the Western world.  It is
changing the way we communicate and interact, replacing regular mail
and even the telephone.  Along with instant messaging, it is altering
our interactions and our work and play behavior, defining new language
and "phrases".  It is interesting to look at email use and understand
its patterns of usage and the social networks it defines.  Looking at
who corresponds with who, when and how frequently tells us about
interactions. Do people send mail backward and forward to each other
or are some interactions unidirectional?  Are some people connected
only by receiving mail from a shared sender?  Without looking at
message contents, we can infer whether attachments, regular or
one-line messages are being sent.  And how does this change over time,
and at what timescales?


<section>
<title>An Overview of email delivery</title>


The way email messages are delivered is quite interesting.  It is a
complex task, as exhibited by the delivery of physical mail by Post
Offices around the world, and yet this complex task is performed
within seconds for electronic mail.  When we send mail, it is
transported from our mail composer to a mail server.  From there, it
is directed to the target domain.  This relay uses TCP/IP and the
internet to jump across intermediate nodes to reach the target
destination.  The mail server on that machine is listening on a port
and the two servers have a short dialog while exchanging the mail.
When that server accepts the mail, it can then send it on to another
machine to deliver it internally. This is like the mail room in large
institutions that then handle delivering it to local departments, etc.
And so the relaying continues within this sub hierarchy of machines
and user logins until it ends at the desired recipient or the message
is rejected by some server. In that case, a message is returned to the
original sender using the same mechanism. 

<para/>

 The situation is slightly complicated by the presence of aliases.
These allow us to refer to one or more people by a single address.  We
use these in our address books to refer to things like our families, a
lunch group, a subgroup of colleagues or students involved in a
project.  When the mail is sent, the alias is expanded by the sender
to include the individual recipients before the mail server is
contacted.  So there is no complexity here. Where aliases are more
interesting is when they are expanded on the server.  A message can be
received by a server addressed to bob and StatDepartment. The server
can then send the message to everyone listed in that alias for
StatDepartment.  So it is not always sufficient to look at the set of
recipients on the original message to know precisely who will recive
it. Instead, we must consider dynamically expanded aliases at
different relay points.

<section>
<title>Mail Logs and Queues</title>
Now that we have a very basic understanding of how mail delivery
works, we can consider how we can access information about who sends
mail to who, when, the size of the message, etc.

Essentially, when we send the mail, we put the message into our local
server's queue. Each entry in the queue is assigned a unique
identifier (a qid). The message goes into the queue as being accepted.
A message is written to the log file identifying this action.
<literal>

</literal>
Shortly after this, the server will process the message and figure out
what to do with it. It may deliver it to the local recipients
directly.
It does this and records the fact by putby inserting 

</article>
