<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org">

 <artheader>
  <title>
Physicians' Reactions Patient Size
 <footnote>
   <para>Adapted from the Rice Virtual Lab on
    <ulink href="http://www.ruf.rice.edu/%7Elane/case_studies/weight/index.html">
    Physicians' Reactions to Patient Size</ulink>. Originally written by David Lane.
    Adapted as a dynamic document by Nan Lui.
   </para>
  </footnote>
 </title>
 </artheader>

<invisible>
<r:init>
library(lattice)
library(plotrix)
library(e1071)
wNt=read.table("weightData.txt", header=TRUE)
wNt$WEIGHT = factor(wNt$WEIGHT, labels=c("Average","Overweight"))
avg = wNt$TIME[wNt$WEIGHT == "Average"]
over = wNt$TIME[wNt$WEIGHT == "Overweight"]
  </r:init>
 </invisible>


<section>
<title>
Background
</title>

<para>
Currently, almost one in every two Americans is overweight and one in
every five is obese. These individuals face discrimination on a daily
basis in employment, education, and relationship contexts. They are
viewed as having a physical, moral and emotional impairment and there
is a tendency for others to hold them responsible for their
condition. Physicians -- people who are trained to treat all their
patients warmly and have access to literature suggesting
uncontrollable and hereditary aspects of obesity -- also believe obese
individuals are undisciplined and suffer from controllability
issues. The current research, conducted by <ulink
url="http://www.ruf.rice.edu/%7Ehebl/">Mikki Hebl</ulink> at Rice
University and Jingping Xu, examines physicians' treatment of obesity
in their patients more systematically by extending past research to
look at physicians' behavioral intentions as well as their expressed
attitudes toward male and female patients who are of average weight,
overweight, or obese. Although past studies tend to compare only
overweight and average-weight individuals, this study provides a novel
look at multiple increments of overweight by including both overweight
and obesity. However, to simplify the presentation of this case study,
only the average and overweight conditions will be presented.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>
Experimental Design
</title>

<para>
A total of 122 primary care physicians affiliated with one of three
major hospitals in the Texas Medical Center of Houston participated in
the study. These physicians were sent a packet containing <!--xref
linkend="figform1" endterm="a medical chart"/ --> similar to the one
they view upon seeing a patient. This chart portrayed a patient who
was displaying symptoms of a migraine headache but was otherwise
healthy. Two variables (the gender and the weight of the patient) were
manipulated across six different versions of the medical charts. The
weight of the patient, described in terms of Body Mass Index (BMI),
was average (BMI = 23), overweight (BMI = 30), or obese (BMI =
36). Physicians were randomly assigned to receive one of the six
charts, were asked to look over the chart carefully, and then complete
two medical forms.  The second form asked physicians which of 42 tests
that they would recommend giving to the patient. The second form asked
physicians to indicate how much time they believed they would spend
with the patient, and to describe the reactions that they would have
toward this patient.
</para>

<para>
In this presentation, only the question on how much time the
physicians believed they would spend with the patient is
analyzed. Although three patient weight conditions were used in the
study (average, overweight, and obese) only the average and overweight
conditions will be analyzed. Therefore, there are two levels of
patient weight (average and overweight) and one dependent variable
(time spent).
</para>
</section>


<section>
<title>
Descriptive Statistics
</title>

<para>
Histograms of the time expected to be spent with the average-weight
and overweight patients are shown below.
</para>

<figure id="fig:histogram">

<r:plot showCode="false" width="900" height="800">
histogram(~TIME | WEIGHT, data=wNt)

<!-- Nan's code
par(mfrow=c(2,1), mai=c(0.5, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5))

hist(wNt[wNt[,1]=="Average",2], xlab="", main="Average Weight", xlim=c(0, 60), breaks=12) 
hist(wNt[wNt[,1]=="Overweight",2], xlab="", main="Overweight", xlim=c(0, 60), breaks=12)
-->


</r:plot>
</figure>

<r:code>
res = tapply(wNt$TIME, wNt$WEIGHT, function(x) {
  c(length(x), mean(x), median(x), min(x), max(x), quantile(x, p=0.25), 
  quantile(x, p=0.75), sd(x), std.error(x), skewness(x), kurtosis(x) ) })

 res = sapply(res, function(x) x)
 rownames(res) = c("N", "Mean", "Median", 
  "Minimum", "Maximum", "25th Perc", "75th Perc", 
  "SD", "STD Err", "Skew", "Kurtosis")
  res
</r:code>

<para>
Box plots comparing the time expected to be spent with the
average-weight and overweight patients are shown below.
</para>

<figure id="fig:boxplot">

<r:plot showCode="false" width="900" height="800">
bwplot(TIME ~ WEIGHT, data=wNt)
<!-- boxplot(TIME ~ WEIGHT, data=wNt, ylab="Expected Time")  -->
</r:plot>

</figure>

</section>

<section>
<title>
Inferential Statistics
</title>

<para>
An independent t test was used to test for differences between
groups. This test assumes normality and homogeneity of
variance. Although the distributions are not quite normal, they are
not so deviant as to make the test invalid. The standard deviations
for the average group and the overweight group are 

<r:code  showCode="false" digits="3">
res["SD",]
</r:code>

Therefore there is no reason to suspect a violation of the homogeneity
of variance assumption.

<invisible>
<r:code>
TwNt = t.test( TIME ~ WEIGHT, data=wNt)
pval = TwNt$p.value
sig=pval &lt; 0.05
</r:code>
</invisible>

</para>

<para>
The t(69) statistic is <r:expr digits="3">TwNt$statistic</r:expr>, and
the p-value is <r:expr digits="3">pval</r:expr>.  The t-test is
<r:expr> if(!sig)"not"</r:expr> significant. We <r:expr>
if(!sig)"do not"</r:expr> reject the null hypothesis of no difference
between groups at the 5 percent level.  The 95% confidence interval on
the difference between means extends from <r:expr
digits="3">TwNt$conf.int[1]</r:expr> to <r:expr
digits="3">TwNt$conf.int[2]</r:expr>. Therefore, there is
<r:expr>if(!sig)"no"</r:expr> strong evidence that physicians expect
to spend less time with overweight patients.
</para>

</section>
</article>
