<?xml version='1.0'?>

<article xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">


<comment>Showing/Hiding Code: It would be nice to be able to hide all of the code, but have a
button at the top of the document that says "Show All Code" to show all the code in 
the document.  In addition, it would be nice to have a "See Code" button after all plots, 
functions, or data that you see so you could look only at individual chunks of code you
choose while you're reading.</comment>

<comment>Making a Table: The summary statistics matrix that is commented out would be a nice way to 
see the data, but I'd like to be able to put it in a table with grid lines instead of just a
matrix as it is.</comment>

<comment>Digits Attribute: I want to run the file using the summary statistics matrix way just 
once to make sure it works with the digits attribute that I've recently added.</comment>

<comment>Last para of section should hyperlink at "here"...is that really a figure?  First of all, 
the webpage itself is messed up.</comment>

<comment>How do I do the materials page? Is a hyperlink to the table best?  I don't think so
since eventually the point is not to copy other people's work.</comment>

<comment>What's the difference between Sect and Section? How to layer them?  Only 5 sects. 
Can I put sections inside sections as I did? I need a better way to organize sections mostly 
because of the size of titles and organizational look.</comment>

<comment>Add section5 on Inferential Statistics</comment>

<comment>I could get a picture of a gun on there by a hyperlink.  Is there a better way?</comment>


<comment>This was my original way of showing the summary statistics because it is more
similar to what can be seen on Rice's website.  The was chosen to be seen below, however,
is just as good and simpler.</comment>


<r:code id="SummaryStats" digits="3" eval="false">
SummaryStats =
matrix(c(min(words[,1]),max(words[,1]),mean(words[,1]),sd(words[,1]),min(words[,2]),
max(words[,2]),mean(words[,2]),sd(words[,2]),min(words[,3]),max(words[,3]),mean(words[,3]),sd(words[,3]),
min(words[,4]),max(words[,4]),mean(words[,4]),sd(words[,4])),4,4,byrow=T)
colnames(SummaryStats) = c("Min","Max","Mean","SD")
rownames(SummaryStats) =
c("WeaponAggressive","NonWeaponAggressive","WeaponNonAggressive",
"NonWeaponNonAggressive")
SummaryStats
</r:code>


</article>
