<?xml version='1.0'?>

<article xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<invisible>
<r:code id="words">
words = matrix(c(44.6667,44,43.2409,45.1564,
42.7083,43.7273,46.8628,45.1278,
41.6957,41.8182,44.4939,43.3712,
34.7778,37.1364,35.2715,34.4035,
47.0833,44.3478,46.2482,46.3137,
39.7727,41.7647,42.9762,42.1587,
44.125,44.6667,43.5898,43.6742,
41.1667,42.2917,41.5536,39.4447,
41.619,45.1304,41.803,43.173,
38.7083,32.2083,38.7615,39.4606,
38.5833,37.5417,38.22,38.214,
38.125,38.875,38.6709,39.4718,
42.8333,43.0417,42.7684,42.6061,
35.7917,38.3333,36.8816,37.8219,
33.3158,34.3125,30.0319,29.4278,
43.7826,43.7619,43.5041,43.6543,
49.7727,54.0952,50.7373,55.4451,
28.5556,31.1176,28.8856,26.8333,
33.7059,34.1765,34.6903,31.7301,
38.6667,39.0435,37.7833,38.4417,
41.1364,40.2609,38.3768,40.0405,
52.9545,54.3913,54.9234,53.7414,
44.125,42.6364,43.0367,42.6009,
44.125,42.6364,43.0367,42.6009,
44.625,42.7727,44.5337,43.3814,
39.8261,41.875,42.2875,42.6104,
40.2174,41.125,42.7546,42.9607,
30.1176,34.4118,33.6941,31.9481,
43.25,42.625,44.6222,44.6203,
47.9048,49.1739,49.8551,49.8009,
39.1304,38.0833,39.9209,39.7252,
42.5217,46.0833,42.6268,42.7801),32,4,byrow=T)
words = as.data.frame(words)
names(words) =
c("WeaponAggressive","NonWeaponAggressive",
  "WeaponNonAggressive", "NonWeaponNonAggressive")
</r:code>
</invisible>

<artheader>
 <title>Weapons and Agression
  <footnote>
   <para>Adapted from the Rice Virtual Lab on
    <ulink href="http://www.ruf.rice.edu/%7Elane/case_studies/guns/index.html">
    Weapons and Agression</ulink>.  Originally written by David Lane.
    Adapted as a dynamic document by Jamie Julin.
   </para>
  </footnote>
 </title>

</artheader>


<section><title>Background</title>
<figure id="pdf">
<graphic fileref="gun.JPG">
</graphic>
</figure>

<para>
The <quote>weapons effect</quote> is the finding that the presence of
a weapon or even a picture of a weapon can cause people to behave more
aggressively. Although once a controversial finding, the weapons
effect is now a well-established phenomenon. One explanation of the
weapons effect is that because guns have been associated with
aggression, seeing a gun increases the accessibility of associated
aggressive thoughts which in turn facilitate aggressive behavior. The
idea that activation of a concept in semantic memory increases
activation and therefore accessibility of related concepts is called
spreading activation and has been demonstrated in numerous
experimental studies. If this spreading activation explanation of the
weapons effect is correct, then the presence of a weapon word (such as
<quote>dagger</quote> or <quote>bullet</quote>) should increase the
accessibility of an aggressive word (such as <quote>destroy</quote> or
<quote>wound</quote>). The accessibility of a word can be measured by
the time it takes to name a word presented on computer screen. The
current study <citation><biblioref
linkend="bib:Anderson98"/></citation> tested this hypothesis.
</para>

</section>



<section><title>Experimental Design</title>
<para>
The hypothesis is that a person can name an aggressive word more
quickly if it is preceded by a weapon word than if it word is preceded
by a neutral word. Each subject named both aggressive and
non-agressive words following both weapon and non-weapon
<quote>primes.</quote> The design, therefore, was a 2 (prime type:
weapon vs. nonweapon) x 2 (target type: aggressive vs. nonagressive)
within-subjects factorial design. Each subject was given a total of
192 trials, 48 in each of the four prime type x target type
combinations. The means of the times in each of these four conditions
were used as the dependent variables. Therefore, each subject provided
four scores to the analysis.
</para>

<para>
The <r:expr>dim(words)[2]</r:expr> subjects were undergraduate
students ranging in age between 18 and 24 years. They were told that
the purpose of this study was to test reading ability of various
words.  On each of the 192 trials, a computer presented a priming
stimulus word (either a weapon or non-weapon word) for 1.25 seconds, a
blank screen for 0.5 seconds, and then a target word (agressive or
nonagressive word). The experimenter instructed the subjects to read
the first word to themselves and then to read the second word out loud
as quickly as they could. The computer recorded reaction times.
</para>
</section>



<section><title>Materials</title>

</section>



<section><title>Descriptive Statistics</title>
<section><title>Box Plots</title>


<para>
When comparing experimental conditions, it is always a good idea to
construct parallel box plots as shown below.
</para>

<r:plot id="boxplots">
boxplot(words)
</r:plot>

<para>
Generally speaking, the time it took to name an aggressive word was
faster when the target word was preceded by a weapon word.  A
comparison of the non-aggressive target words reveals no evidence of a
weapon prime versus non-weapon prime having an effect.
</para>

</section>


<section><title>Histogram</title>

<para>
The presence of outside values (dots in the box plots) suggests that
the distributions have slightly more scores in their tails than would
be expected in a normal distribution.  A histogram of the
weapon-nonaggressive combination is shown below.
</para>

<r:plot id="histogram">
hist(words$WeaponNonAggressive, 10, xlab="Reponse Time", ylab="Frequency",
 main="Histogram of Weapon NonAggressive")
</r:plot>

</section>


<section><title>Summary Statistics</title>

<para>
The mean and standard deviations of the four conditions are shown below.
</para>


<r:code>
summary(words, digits =3)
</r:code>

</section>


<section><title>QQ-Plots</title>

<para>
Since many inferential statistical procedures assume the data are
normally distributed, Normal probability plots (also called Q-Q plots
or Normal Quantile plots) are helpful tools to determine if the data
is normally distributed. Basically these plots plot the sample
quantiles from the data set against the quantiles of the normal
distribution.  If the data are from the same normal distribution, the
data should fall along the line y=x.  Even though the data do not fall
exactly on this line, the deviations are not extreme.
</para>

<r:plot id="QQ">
par(mfrow=c(2,2))
qqnorm(words[,1],main="Weapon Aggressive")
qqline(words[,1])
qqnorm(words[,2],main="NonWeapon Aggressive")
qqline(words[,2])
qqnorm(words[,3],main="Weapon NonAggressive")
qqline(words[,3])
qqnorm(words[,4],main="NonWeapon NonAggressive")
qqline(words[,4])
</r:plot>

</section>

</section>


<section><title>Experiment 2</title>
<para>
Experiment 2 replicated the effect using pictures rather than words as
primes. Weapon pictures primed aggressive words more than they primed
non-aggressive words and this difference was significantly greater
than it was for the neutral picture primes.
</para>
</section>



<section><title>Conclusion</title>

<para>
Both experiments showed that the mere identification of a weapon
primes aggression-related thoughts. These findings support the
hypothesized explanation of the weapons effect.
</para>

</section>


<bibliography  xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
         xmlns:omg="http://www.omegahat.org"
         xmlns:bioc="http://www.bioconductor.org"
         xmlns:js="http://www.r-project.org"
         xmlns:jsx="http://www.ecmascript.org">

<biblioentry id="bib:Anderson98">
<title>Does the gun pull the trigger?  Automatic priming effects of
weapon pictures and weapon names.</title>
<authorgroup>
<author><firstname>C</firstname><othername
role="mi">A</othername><surname>Anderson</surname></author>

<author><firstname>A</firstname><othername
role="mi">J</othername><surname>Benjamin</surname></author>

<author><firstname>B</firstname><othername
role="mi">D</othername><surname>Bartholow</surname></author>

</authorgroup>
<publisher><publishername>Psychological Science</publishername></publisher>
<pubdate>1998</pubdate>

<!--  9, 308-314. -->
</biblioentry>

</bibliography>

</article>
