<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "file:///usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.1.2-1.0-8/docbookx.dtd">

<section>
<title> Acceptance/Rejection Sampling</title>

<para/> We use the acceptance/rejection method of generating random numbers
when we do not have a random number generator for the probability
distribution of interest and the CDF does not have a closed form solution
so the inverse CDF method does not apply.

<para/>
The acceptance/rejection method relies on two simple properties
related to sampling from the uniform distribution over a region in the plane.
Figure xxx shows a region, B, in the (x,y) plane.
A random sample of size n from the uniform distribution on B, would yield
random pairs (x_j, y_j) where the chance that a particular pair falls in some 
subregion C is the same for all subregions of the same area, and this chance is
Area (C)/Area(B).
We consider each property in turn. 

<para/>
The first property is based on the density function of a probability distribution.
For a continuous CDF, F, the density function is the derivative of the CDF,
typically denoted by <math:variable>f</math:variable>. 
The density function is nonegative and bounded.
Often times when the CDF is not of closed form, the density function is
of closed form. A common example is the normal distribution, where
the density function for the standard normal is
<equation>
phi(x) =  1/sqrt(2pi) exp( -0.5x^2)
</equation>

<para/>
First property: 
For a probability density function <math:fcn>f</math:fcn> on a compact interval, 
say [0,1],
consider the region in two dimensions formed by the points (x.y) bounded by the
x-axis, y-axis, x = 1, and y = f(x). Call this region B.
See figure  xxx for an example.
If points (x_1,y_1), ... (x_n,y_n) are generated at random from the uniform
distribution on region B, then the x-values will have CDF F (and density f).

<para/>
To see that this is the case, we need only determine the CDF of the generated
x_j from the (x_j, y_j) pairs.  For any specific value x, the area under density
f to the left of x, is F(x). This follows because f is the derivative of F.
The chance that the randomly generated pair (x_j, y_j) falls in this region
is F(x) because the Area(B) = 1. 

<para/>
If we could generate data from the uniform distribution on this region B, then
we would have a random sample from the probability distribution of interest.
Unfortunately, this is typically not the case. For if we could generate
numbers uniformly from B then typically we would also be able to generate
numbers via the inverse CDF method.  The next property helps us out of this
problem.

<para/>
Second property: 
For a region <math:variable>A</math:variable> that contains a subregion 
<math:variable>B</math:variable>,
suppose we take a uniform random sample of <math:variable>n</math:variable> points 
from <math:variable> A</math:variable>,
and <math:variable>m</math:variable> of the <math:variable>n</math:variable> 
points fall in subregion <math:variable>B</math:variable>. See figure xxx, for an example.
Then those points that fall in <math:variable>B</math:variable> will form a uniform 
random sample of <math:variable>m</math:variable> 
points from <math:variable>B</math:variable>.

<para/>
This means that if we are able to include the region formed by the density f in a
larger region where we do have the tools to sample from the larger region, the
we simply discard those points that fall outside of the region of interest, and
take the x-coordinates to get a sample from F.  Note that if the containing
region is much bigger than the region formed by the density then we will be
discarding many points, and we need to continue sampling until n points fall
in the density's region.

<para/>
Clearly, the acceptance/rejection method is not as efficient as the inverse CDF method.
It generates two numbers, the x-coordinate and the y-coordinate, and discards the
y-coordinate, and it discards (x, y) pairs from the region outside the area formed
by the density and the x-axis.

<para/>
In practice, the larger region A is formed by scaling another density function g
so that c*g ge f for all x.
In order to do this, the support of g must contain the support of f, 
i.e. if g(x)>0 then f(x)>0. 
We choose the density function g to be one where we have
a random number generator for the corresponding distribution.
We can always firnd such a generator, for in the worstr case, we can select the 
uniform distribution on the support of f.  
Then to generate (x,y) pairs at random from the region
between c*g and the x-axis, we first generate x-values from g, and for each x-value,
generate a y-value uniformly between 0 and cg(x). If the resulting y is less than
f(x) then x is kept as part of the sample, otherwise it is discarded. 
 
<exercise>
<question>
Use the acceptance/rejection method with the uniform distribution 
to generate 100 observations from the standard normal distribution.
Keep track of the (x,y) coordinates of all the numbers generated 
(both the rejected and accepted).
Plot these numbers on the (x,y) plane and overlay the plot with
the normal curve.
</question>
<question>
Use the acceptance/rejection method with the beta(x,x) distribution 
to generate 100 observations from the standard normal distribution.
Keep track of the (x,y) coordinates of all the numbers generated 
(both the rejected and accepted).
Plot these numbers on the (x,y) plane and overlay the plot with
the normal curve.
Do you think that this approach was more efficient than the first?
This is not the approach used to generate normals in the rnorm function.
Describe it?
</question>

<question>
Use a modification of the acceptance rejection method from part 2 above
to generate pseudo-random numbers from the standard normal contaminatedat 
at the 5% level with observations from the normal with mean 3 and sd 0.1.
</question>

<answer>
</answser>  
</exercise>

</section>

