<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
         xmlns:s="http://cm.bell-labs.com/stat/S4">

<title>Homework 1: Reading <SPAM/> data</title>

A collection of <SPAM/> data is available in the R package
<r:package>RSpamData</r:package>.  The dare were obtained from <ulink
url="http://spamassassin.org/publiccorpus/">http://spamassassin.org/publiccorpus/</ulink>,
which is a widely used <SPAM/> filter in  use today.

<para/>
There are 5 directories in the dataset: 3 contain regular mail, 2
contain spam.  There are over 9,000 messages in all.
Your tasks in this homework are to
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
 "Read" the data into R 
</listitem>
<listitem>
 Explore the data and see if you can find any patterns
 to spam and regular mail that would allow us to
 identify either in some "automated" manner.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

Each message is as it would appear in your mail folder.  It consists
of header information and the text of the message.  The text is just
the regular text one would read and that somebody wrote for the
recipient.  In this simple format, attachments are identified in 
very simply ways, typically separate by a "Boundary" identifier
and "Next part"

The header information is analogous to an envelope in physical
mail. It identifies the intended receiver and, for regular mail, the
identify of the sender.  It has a time and date stamp to say when it
was sent.  It has routining information about what machines it was
sent through on its way from the sender to the recipient.  There is
information about the subject matter, whether this is a fresh topic or
sent in reply to an existing mail message.  Each mail agent is
entitled to add its own information to the header.  Fields such as
mailing list information are often added.  Likewise, sometimes the
name of the program which was used to compose the mail is included in
the headers.  The MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) type of
the message identifying the format of the body



<section>
<title>Reading the Data into R</title>

What do want to end up with?

We want a collection of all the mail messages in the directories.
Each message should be broken into its header information, the body
and an indicator whether it is spam or not.  The body can be broken
into the regular text, included messages and attachments. For the
moment, we will not do that.

The header should be represented as a named vector
giving the header field and its value.
You will have to deal with entries in the header that
span multiple lines, e.g.
<literallayout>
<![CDATA[
Received: from localhost (localhost [127.0.0.1])
	by phobos.labs.netnoteinc.com (Postfix) with ESMTP id E3D7B47C66
	for <zzzz@localhost>; Thu, 22 Aug 2002 09:54:39 -0400 (EDT)
]]>
</literallayout>
Note that all of these "continuation" lines can be identified
by the fact that they are indented, i.e. start with white space.

We identify whether the message is spam or not from the directory in
which it is located.  The messages in the directories spam and spam_2
are <SPAM/>, the remainder are not.

<para/>
What sort of R data structure should you use to store the data?
Think about the nature of each "record" and also what we will
want to do with in the next stage of the homework.

</section>

<section>
<title>Exploring the Data</title>

Once you have the data, explore it to understand what we have and the
basic characteristics of the mail messages.  You might be interested
in some of the following:

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
   the distribution of the length of a message
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   the distribution of the number of attachments
  (can we identify attachments in the messages?)
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   information about who sends mail, who receives mail
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   the times that messages are sent
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  What mail programs ("User-agent"s in the headers)
  are common? Are there data on this?
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Some of these are not interesting!

<para/> 

Are there differences in the distributions of these variables
for spam and regular mail?  How we can see this? Are these real
differences, do you think? or just artifacts of this 
particular dataset?

</section>

<section>
<title>Useful R Commands</title>
R commands that might be useful are

<s:functionRef>list.files</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>readLines</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>strsplit</s:functionRef>,

<s:functionRef>plot</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>hist</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>boxplot</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>summary</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>table</s:functionRef>,


<s:functionRef>list.files</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>nchar</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>substring</s:functionRef>,



<s:functionRef>grep</s:functionRef>
<s:functionRef>gsub</s:functionRef>

<s:functionRef>sapply</s:functionRef> and <s:functionRef>lapply</s:functionRef>,
<s:functionRef>scan</s:functionRef>.
</section>


<section>
<title>To Hand in</title>

Prepare a short report discussing both the processing of the data to
get it into the system and what you discovered when exploring the
data. You should describe
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
  what you did to read the data in,
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  what challenges you encountered with data, 
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  the 3 (or more) most interesting statistical features of the data.
  Some of these features should relate to the differences, or lack
  thereof, between  regular mail and spam.
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  Demonstrate and justify these features using
  numerical and graphical summaries.
 </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>

</article>



<!-- Use the code to catch errors in your understanding   -->








