<section  xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org">
<title>Traffic flow on highways in California</title>
<para> 
Tohe data available for this lab assignment can be found on the web at
<ulink url="http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/users/nolan/stat133/data/flow-occ-table.txt">
www.stat.berkeley.edu/users/nolan/stat133/data/flow-occ-table.txt
</ulink>
</para>
<para>
These data have been collected by loop detectors at one particular
location of eastbound Interstate 80 in Sacramento, California. There
are six columns and 1740 rows in the data set. The rows correspond to
successive five minute intervals from March 14 to 20, 2003, where the
data values in a row report the flow (number of cars) and occupancy
(the proportion of time there was a car over the loop) in each of
three lanes on the freeway. Lane 1 is the leftmost lane, lane 2 is in
the center, and lane 3 is the rightmost. The original data are from
the Freeway Performance Measurement System (PEMS) website
<ulink url="http://pems.eecs.berkeley.edu/Public/"/>
</para>
<qandaset>
 <para>Your tasks for this assignment are to:</para>
 <qandaentry>
   <question>
   <para>
Read the data directly from the web into R using one of the R
functions readLines, read.table, read.csv, or scan. </para>
   </question>
   <answer>
    <r:code>
traffic = read.csv("http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/users/nolan/stat133/data/flow-occ-table.txt")
    </r:code>
    <para>
We use <r:code>read.csv</r:code> since the default values of the
arguments match the data format - commma separated values with column
names in the first line.
    </para>
   </answer>
 </qandaentry>
 <qandaentry>
  <question>
  <para> Explore the data visually to answer the following questions</para>
   <qandaset>
     <qandaentry>
       <question>
        <para> Examine the relationships of the flows in the three
        lanes using boxplots. Is the statement, <quote>The flow in
        lane 2 is typically about 50% higher than in lane 3,</quote>
        an accurate description of the relationship you found? Explain
        in one sentence.</para>
       </question>
       <answer>
         <!-- I want to display the code and the plot from the code  -->
         <r:code>boxplot(traffic$Flow1, traffic$Flow2, traffic$Flow3)</r:code>
         <para>
The statement is somewhat accurate: the median flow in lane 2 looks
about 50% higher than lane 3, however this statement ignores the fact
that the spread of the values is also much larger in lane 2, the IQR
in lane 2 is <r:expr>IQR(traffic$Flow2</r:expr> in comparison to
<r:expr>IQR(Traffic$Flow3)</r:expr> for lane 3.
         </para>
       </answer>
     </qandaentry>
     <qandaentry>
      <question> 
       <para>
Consider the flows in the three lanes using time series plots. Which
lane typically serves the most traffic? Is the statement, <quote>When one
lane is congested, the others are too,</quote> an accurate description of the
relationship you found?
       </para>
      </question>
      <answer>
      <r:plot>
plot(traffic$Flow1, type = "l")
lines(traffic$Flow2, col = "blue")
lines(traffic$Flow3, col = "red")
      </r:plot>
      <para>
Lane 1 has the highest peaks however it also has the lowest
troughs. The majority of the time lane 2 appears to have higher flow
than lane 1. So, lane 2 serves the most traffic. When one lane is
congested the others are too.  This is an accurate statmenet because
the flows move together - when one lane has high flow so do the
others.
      </para>
      </answer>
      </qandaentry>
   </qandaset>
   <note type="hint" level="2">
    <para>A level 2 hint.</para>
   </note>
   <note type="hint" level="0">
    <para>A level 0 hint.</para>
   </note>
  </question>
 </qandaentry>
 <qandaentry>
  <question>
    <para> 
Consider the relationship between flow and occupancy. Plot flow
against occupancy for lane 1. In one sentence, describe the shape of
the points. Relate the shape you see to a propoerty of traffic. Is
this relationship born out in the other two lanes. Explain any
similarities and differences that you find.
    </para>
  </question>
  <answer>
   <r:code>
par(mfrow = c(1, 3))
plot(traffic$Occ1, traffic$Flow1)
plot(traffic$Occ2, traffic$Flow2)
plot(traffic$Occ3, traffic$Flow3)
   </r:code>
   <para>
The majority of the points lie on a positively sloping line but there
is also a cluster of points off this line.
   </para>
   <para>
In smooth flowing traffic the number of cars passing over the loop and
the percentage of time it is covered is proportional. This explains
the linear relationship. Once flow exceeds a certain value this
relationship breaks down and the traffic becomes congested. This
explains the points that do not follow the linear relationship.
   </para>
   <para>
This relationship is born out in the other two lanes. However, the
breakdown happens at lower values of flow (about 130 for lane 2 and
100 for lane 3).
   </para>
  </answer>
 </qandaentry>
 </qandaset>

  <para>
Consider using the R functions <r:func>plot</r:func>,
<r:func>boxplot</r:func>, <r:func>density</r:func>,
<r:func>hist</r:func>, <r:func>pairs</r:func>, and
<r:func>points</r:func>. Also consider using some of the arguments to
the plotting functions to improve the appearance of your plot, such as
<r:var>ylim</r:var>, <r:var>xlab</r:var>, <r:var>main</r:var>,
<r:var>log</r:var>, <r:var>type</r:var>, <r:var>col</r:var>, and
<r:var>lwd</r:var>.
  </para>
</section>