<article>

<articleinfo>
<title>Relational Databases and Exploratory Data Analysis:  Baseball Data
<para/>
Due: 20th at midnight. 
</title>
</articleinfo>

In this project, you will explore the database containing 22 tables
containing information about baseball players, managers, teams,
colleges, etc.  The goal is to find interesting characteristics of the
data and to provide meaningful summaries of the large collection of
information.  Plots, succinct tables, and if appropriate, models
should be used to illustrate and support your findings.  
The primary topics in this assignment are exploratory data analysis (EDA), 
SQL and visualization.

<para/>

The BaseballDatabank04 database on gcox contains 22 relations/tables.
These provide information about major league baseball teams and
players for the years 1884 through 2004.  The database comes from
<ulink url="http://baseball1.info">http://baseball1.info</ulink> and
was created and licensed by Sean Lahman.  We are entitled to use it
for research use and cannot distribute it further.  And we are
grateful for his efforts in compiling and managing this database.

<para/> The attributes in the different relations are described in
<ulink url="http://baseball1.com/statistics/readme51.txt">Baseball
Archive documentation</ulink>.

<para/>
Other sites for baseball data include
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
<ulink url="http://asp.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/salaries/default.aspx">
http://asp.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/salaries/default.aspx
</ulink>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
<ulink url="http://www.baseball-databank.org/">
http://www.baseball-databank.org/
</ulink>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para/>


You can pose or create questions that most interest you and that
hopefully lead to interesting exploration of the data, of accessing
the relational database, or composing and creating displays.  The goal
is to illustrate aspects of using a relational database, understanding
how and when to perform some commands in a database and others in R,
and what and how to plot to display attributes of data.  You should
explore one or more questions that allow you to illustrate each of
these skills.


<para/> Below are some questions you might consider if you are having
difficulty coming up with your own.  You are strongly encouraged to
find others, and you will get credit for working on your own
questions.  You can get inspiration from other sources such as Web
sites, newspaper articles, journals, etc.  In such cases, your task is
to do the necessary computations and explain them.
 The more work and questions you do, the more credit you will get.  So
 this is an opportunity to shine.  (But don't go over-board and let
 other classes suffer, of course.)   Not all the questions below
are equally difficult, so it is not possible to say "do k of these".
I am thinking that your report should be about 4 or 5 pages, not
including figures and tables (but counting code). You can go into
detail in a few questions, or do the basics on several questions.
If the questions you  chose are simple one or two line SQL commands,
then you will need to do more of them. If they are involved
SQL commands and plots and interpretation, then 4 or 5 of them
will be sufficient.

<para/> 


Visualization is a complex art.  Determining how to compose plots
and present different attributes requires design.  Then creating the
display in software is technical.  You should explore these two
aspects, asking questions when you want.  I have provided some <ulink
url="gallery.html">example plots</ulink> with code to get the data and
create the basic plot.


<para/>

You might find the following functions and the related ones found on
their help pages useful:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
by(), table()
</listitem>
<listitem>
boxplot(), legend(), lines(), points(),
axis(), etc.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
The lattice package may also prove useful for creating plots with
different panels for levels of factors, etc.

<para/>

If you think R might have a function to do something
you want to do, use the help.search()
and help.start() facilities in R or ask on the
class bulletin board.



<questions>
<question>
How many people are included in the databases?
</question>

<question>
Are all of these players?  How many are players? how many are
managers? and how many are both?
</question>

<question>
What is the earliest season recorded in this database?  and the most
recent?
<answer>
<sql>
SELECT DISTINCT yearID from Teams;
</sql>

SELECT MAX(yearID), MIN(yearID) from Teams;

Do we need to look over the other tables to see if there was an
earlier record.  This depends on the model for the database and its
integrity constraints.
Can we concatenate the years from
the pitcher and batter statistics?

<sql>
SELECT yearID AS year FROM Batting 
 UNION DISTINCT 
SELECT yearID AS year FROM Pitching
 ORDER BY year;
</sql>
</answer>
</question>


<question>
What college produced the largest number of major league baseball
players? Is there a geographical  trend?
How many colleges are there in total?
And how many players didn't go to college at all?
<answer>
<sql>
select college, COUNT(*) as Number FROM Master GROUP BY college ORDER BY  Number DESC;
</sql>

<sql>
select DISTINCT COUNT(college) FROM Master;
</sql>
doesn't give the right answer.

We could issue the query
<sql>
select DISTINCT college FROM Master;
</sql>
and count the number of tuples.
We'd like to be able to do this in the database itself
rather than transferring all the tuples that we don't necessarily
want.

XXX
Alternatively, we can 
select DISTINCT college FROM Master GROUP BY college;
</answer>
</question>


<question>
Can we tell who won the "World" series in a given year?

<answer>
 SELECT SeriesPost.yearID AS Year, Teams.name AS Team FROM Teams, SeriesPost 
   WHERE SeriesPost.round = 'WS' 
     AND Teams.teamID = SeriesPost.teamIDwinner
     AND Teams.yearID = SeriesPost.yearID;
</answer>
</question>

<question>
Who lost the "World" series in each year?
</question>

<question>
Look at the relationship between the number of games
won in a season and winning the world series?
And similarly relate these to payroll.
</question>

<question>
For 1999, compute the payrolls of the different teams?
Can we do this for all years in a single SQL statement?

<answer>
If you do this interactively in MySQL, you will run out of memory.  A
problem in client/server computing is "which application ran out of
memory" or reported the error?

In contrast with the MySQL shell, doing it in R works fine and doing
it in blocks via <r>fetch(rs, n = 100)</r> would be even less
stressful on the memory requirements.

<r>
rs = dbSendQuery(con, "select CONCAT(nameFirst, ' ', nameLast) AS Name, Salaries.yearID, Salaries.salary FROM Master, Teams, Salaries WhERE Salaries.yearID > 2000 AND Salaries.yearID = Teams.yearID AND Master.playerID = Salaries.playerID AND Teams.teamID = Salaries.teamID;")
</r>

<r>
d = dbGetQuery(con, "select Salaries.yearID AS Year, Teams.name AS Team, SUM(Salaries.salary) AS Payroll FROM Master, Teams, Salaries WhERE Salaries.yearID = Teams.yearID AND Master.playerID = Salaries.playerID AND Teams.teamID = Salaries.teamID GROUP BY Team, Year ORDER BY Team, Year;")
</r>
</answer>
</question>

<question>
Plot the payrolls over years for the different teams.  What plot types
are good for showing this data?  Contrast different graphical
techniques.  Information for inflation rates from 1986 to the present
is available in the database inflation and in the relation
AnnualRates.  You might consider using this to adjust/control the
dollar amounts for inflation.

<para/>
Superimpose the payroll of the two teams that made it to the "World
Series" on this plot.  Is there a relationship?  How about for the
teams that made it into the playoffs in a year?

<answer>
<r>
plotPayrolls =
function(d, dd = by(d, d[,"Team"], function(x) x), ..., xlab = "Year", ylab = "Payroll")
{
 plot(0, xlim = range(d[,"Year"]), ylim = range(d[,"Payroll"]), type = "n", ..., xlab = xlab, ylab = ylab)
 sapply(1:length(dd), function(i) {
                        lines(dd[[i]][,"Year"], dd[[i]][,"Payroll"], col = i, lty = i) 
                        TRUE
                     })
 legend(min(d[,"Year"]), max(d[,"Payroll"]), names(dd), col = 1:length(dd), lty = 1:length(dd), cex = .90)

 invisible(dd)
}  
</r>

We probably want to standardize by dividing the total or maximum
payroll for each year.

<r>
mx = by(d, d[,1], function(x) max(x[,3]))
maxPayroll = as.vector(mx)
names(maxPayroll) = names(mx)
dd = by(d, d[,"Team"], function(x) x[ ])
d[,"Payroll"] = d[,"Payroll"]/maxPayroll[as.character(d[,"Year"])]
</r>

<r>
jpeg("PayrollYear.jpg", width = 900, height = 900)
plotPayrolls(d, add = FALSE, main = "Payroll for Baseball Teams over years")
boxplot(Payroll ~ Year, data = d,at = 1985:2003, add = TRUE, col="red", lwd=2, notch = TRUE)
dev.off()
</r>
Add NL and AL to this plot by using line width
or plotting characters.

</answer>
</question>

<question>
Show the distributions of the payrolls over years.  We can think of a
boxplot for each year for this.  Again, we can superimpose additional
attributes and even lines connecting the different statistics for
particular teams if they are not very noisy.

<answer>
boxplot(Payroll ~ Year, data = d)

  # Standardize by dividing by the maximum for each year
d[,3] = d[,3]/maxPayroll[as.character(d[,1])]
boxplot(Payroll ~ Year, data = d)
</answer>
</question>


<question>
Look at the payrolls for the teams
that are in the same leagues? and then in the same divisions?
Are there any interesting characteristics?
</question>

<question>
Is the payroll related to the age of the players?  One might expect an
old team to be paying veteran players a lot near the end of their
careers. Teams with a large number of older players would therefore
have a large payroll.  Is there any evidence supporting this?
</question>


<question>
Look at the distribution of salaries of individual
players over time for different teams.
</question>

<question>
Look at players and see whether the distribution
of home runs has increased over the years?
</question>


<question>

Are Hall of Fame players, in general, inducted because of rare,
excellent performances or years or are they rewarded for consistency
over years?

</question>


<question>
Are certain baseball parks better for hitting Home Runs?
Can we tell from this data? Can we make inferences about this
question?
</question>

<question>
Do teams with a few good players and many mediocre players tend to do better
than a team made up more homogeneous talent?
</question>

<question>
Look at the distribution of how well batters do.
Does  this vary over the years?
Do the same players excel each year?
Is there a clustering? a bi-modal distribution?
</question>

<question>
Do pitchers get better with age?  Is there an improvement and then a
fall off in performance?  And is this related to how old they are?
the number of years they have been pitching?  which league they are in
and the designated hitter rule?  Do we have information about each of
these factors and how can we combine them to present information about
the general question?

</question>
</questions>
</article>
